Hi, this is Robert Scheer with another
edition of Scheer Intelligence where the
intelligence comes from my guests,
otherwise this would be a very arrogant
title for a show. And no question, in
fact, John Kiriakou was in the Central
Intelligence Agency what, for 12 years?
14 years. Almost 15 years. So, you are
this is I sometimes say this show
is the poor man's Central Intelligence
Agency, but you were the real deal. And
you actually were involved in the
interrogation capture of the what was
said to be the top person in Al-Qaeda
before Bin Laden was killed. And
you know, so you have vast experience.
The reason I wanted to talk to you I've
talked to you before, it's always
interesting, but I am really this is the
day after we celebrate or two days after
we're recording this, Martin Luther King
Day. And for that occasion in my class I
classes I showed and discussed the movie
made two years ago
by director
and um
it is an incredible movie. It's called
MLK/
FBI.
And it's really about the effort of the
FBI under J. Edgar Hoover to destroy
Martin Luther King first to show he's
some kind of communist
and then when that failed to go after
his personal life and blackmail him and
basically to suicide. And they were
watching him 24/7 when he in fact was
assassinated. That's something I want to
ask you about, but I really want to know
about the deep state in relation to
dissenters like Martin Luther King now
celebrated, honored with a day and so
forth, but at the time we had very
primitive surveillance. They had to
break into his house or a hotel room or
have the hotel room next door and to
entrap them and to get information and
and then fake a letter claiming to
reveal stuff and all that. You were part
of that deep state. What could they do
now? And you watched the movie, you've
thought about it. Uh and I might say one
other news hook here, the Republicans in
Congress are actually reviving a
committee investigation to look at the
excesses of the intelligence agencies,
of the FBI, and so forth. And you wrote
a column saying, "This is not the Church
Committee. We need another Church
Committee." Tell us about the great work
of Frank Church, the Senator from Idaho,
who in the mid-70s revealed so much
about the evil, the the chicanery of our
intelligence agencies. And that directly
bears on the effort to destroy Martin
Luther King.
Yes. Boy, where do you even start with
something like this? Let's start with
with the Church Committee. I wrote a
piece in Consortium News that was
published, I think it was published
today, Wednesday,
about these Republican efforts to
create what they're calling a Church
Committee 2. It's its formal title is
the Select Subcommittee on the
Weaponization of the Federal Government.
I am 1,000%
in favor of creating a Church Committee
2. This is not a Church Committee 2.
Uh this committee is going to be chaired
by Jim Jordan. He's a far-right
Congressman from Ohio, the former
wrestling coach at Ohio State
University. Um he's also the incoming
chairman of the House Judiciary
Committee. And um
he's going to look specifically
at the FBI's targeting of conservatives.
Now, these are conservative parents who
are speaking out at school board
meetings. He's going to look at the FBI
targeting Donald Trump or targeting
anybody deemed to be conservative.
That's not what the Church Committee
did.
The Church Committee
uh
which was bipartisan in nature with
intellectual heavyweights on both sides.
They were looking at crimes being
committed by the deep state. And when I
say the deep state, I mean the CIA, the
FBI, NSA, the Department of the Army,
and associated intelligence
organizations. They were looking at at
the CIA's international assassinations
program, for example. They were looking
at the Army's program to infiltrate
peace groups or anti-Vietnam war groups.
They were looking at the FBI's
surveillance program and spying on
Americans without any warrant or court
order. They would just arbitrarily do it
through a program then called
COINTELPRO.
They looked at the CIA's MKUltra program
in which the CIA
dosed unwitting American citizens with
LSD just to see what their reactions
would be. Just to see if they would talk
about things that they weren't supposed
to talk about while under the influence
of of LSD. People died in these
programs.
Uh this new subcommittee isn't going to
do any such thing. And indeed
Democrats have already said that they're
not going to participate in this
program.
Now, you've got a new speaker of the
house in um
in uh Kevin McCarthy.
He appointed nine Republicans to this
committee, this subcommittee. He's
allowing for six Democrats. The
Democrats aren't going to participate.
The committee was created on a straight
party line vote of 221, all Republicans,
to 211, all Democrats.
Now, compare this to the actual Church
Committee.
Uh it was chaired, of course, by Frank
Church,
uh an intellectual giant who ran for
president in 1976.
It also included Senator Philip Hart of
Michigan, the Hart Senate office.
me let me Okay, let me stop you for a
minute, okay? Can I?
Because we were used No, I mean, what
you're saying is interesting, important.
Your column is good. I republished it
myself uh and share posted morning and
and worth it. But the fact of the matter
is there isn't a Democrat Frank Church
right now.
Frank Church There's not challenged
Democrats. And you know, as as I said in
the beginning, I'm I'm I would like to
talk about with this is so recent after
Martin Luther King Day,
that the invasion of Martin Luther
King's privacy, the attempt to destroy
him, was done by a Democrat president.
Uh it was even started in the
It's a depth on that. It started it with
the JFK, it continued with a vengeance
with Lyndon Johnson. They allowed J.
Edgar Hoover, an obsessed, you know,
fanatic of a man to go after Martin
Luther King
for all sorts of horrible motives,
racist conceits and everything else. Uh
and the fact is I even Bobby Kennedy,
somebody I actually interviewed the
night he was shot and I liked him and
admired his transformation, but the fact
is, as Attorney General he allowed
Hoover to do this
and so and now the Democrats are in a
position of being cheerleading the FBI
it's just wonderful to go as long as
they go after Republicans as long as
they went after Trump. So what I'm
trying to do is get past the partisan
thing here. Yes, these committees should
be better there should be a Frank Church
but there isn't. And the fact we live in
is right. And and this is not a partisan
issue. And and I would point out to you
MSNBC has these FBI CIA people on all
the time as great experts. Okay, I am
looking at
what the voter needs, what the
Constitution requires and I'm taking the
Martin Luther King case as an example.
It's a film if people haven't seen it
MLK forward slash
FBI you get it for 99 cents or something
on Amazon. Watch it and you will
understand what surveillance is about
and the surveillance done on Martin
Luther King is child's play compared to
what can be done on anybody right now.
As somebody who has been a victim of
government prosecution for telling the
truth which is you
I'm wondering
you did what Martin Luther King did.
Martin Luther King got in the crosshairs
of Lyndon Johnson because he came out
against the Vietnam war was denounced
for it by the New York Times and the
Washington Post you know
what's he doing with peace? Well, I he
got a Nobel Peace Prize. He's allowed to
talk about
the Vietnam war and he said my
government is the major provider of
violence in the world today. How do I
tell kids in the ghetto to shun
violence and and so he was punished as
you were for telling the truth And so,
what I want to get though is the
perspective now of of you know, what
what have we learned from a film like
that? What do we see in the modern
society? Because after all, you were in
in the deep state in the modern time
with modern technology. And that's what
I want to talk to you today. I don't we
need we don't need another bashing of
Republicans. We're getting that all over
the place. Oh, no, no. And my intent
here is not to bash Republicans because
the Democrats are equally guilty of all
of these things. This is not a partisan
issue. You know,
you know this statistic, but
but between the the passage of the the
Espionage Act in 1917 and Barack Obama's
election in 2009, three Americans were
were charged with espionage for speaking
to the media. Just during a the Obama
presidency, eight of us were charged
with espionage for speaking to the
media. So, this is not a
Democrats are good, Republicans are bad
situation. It's that all of our elected
officials are bad on this issue. Now,
you you've made an important point here,
and that is the point
uh that technology has improved. It's
improved in ways that
that our political figures of the 1960s
couldn't have even fathomed.
You know, we know thanks to
whistleblowers like Joshua Schulte, a
CIA hacker,
that the CIA, just as an example, as
part of their surveillance program,
can turn your smart TV into a
microphone.
They can they can remotely engineer the
speaker on your TV to act as a
microphone to listen to your
conversations even when the TV is turned
off.
Right? We now know, thanks to the Vault
7 revelations, that the CIA can hack
into the computer system of your car,
take over the car,
and force you off a cliff, off a bridge,
into an abutment or a tree, and kill
you.
And there's nothing you can do to stop
it.
We know, thanks to the Vault 7
revelations, uh that the CIA can uh take
over any computer, even remotely,
anywhere in the world,
and uh and use it against you.
They can do the same with your phone.
They can even when it's off, they can
turn it into a microphone to listen to
anything that you're saying. Now, can
you imagine if the FBI had had that that
kind of capability in 1965?
Or in 1967? It's incredible. In this in
this absolutely brilliant film that
you're talking about, uh MLK FBI,
they talk about the uh
the FBI doing surveillance and and phone
taps and wiretaps on Martin Luther King
and the people around him. They had to
physically go into these people's homes
and unscrew the receiver on their phones
and put a bug into the phone, screw it
back up, and say,
"Thank you. We just uh improved your
phone service." And then they leave.
To the point where one of Martin Luther
King's uh
deputies said to him, "Martin, I think
we're under surveillance. I think they
tapped our phones." And Martin Luther
King responded, "The FBI has far more
important things to worry about than
what we're saying."
Well, in fact,
he was under 24/7 coverage.
They They knew 200 200 agents assigned
to destroying Martin Luther King. Yeah.
And do you remember where they said also
at the highest level
Where Do you remember where they said
also that when Martin Luther King would
travel to different cities, all of the
FBI agents in each of those cities would
literally drop everything they would
they were doing
and spy on Martin Luther King.
Every city that he traveled to. They
were particularly upset because he won
the Nobel Prize. They did not want him
to be a role model. They didn't want him
to be a hero and they didn't support the
civil rights movement. That was one of
their critiques, you know, that they
were not vigorous. They
or we wouldn't have had the problems in
the South that we had. And J. Edgar
Hoover was certainly not a big fan of
that movement. But first he tried to to
brand Martin Luther King a communist
because they found some ex-communists or
old-time guys working as they in the
civil rights movement and advising him
at one point, but that didn't work out.
So they Oh, we got sex here. Let's
destroy him. Let's destroy his marriage.
Let's give a tape to his his wife
purporting to be the noises of people
making love. In those days it was
primitive. So they didn't often have
pictures to go with the tape, but they
said we know he's in that room or what
have you. It's disgusting. And and what
I'm saying is that they what they did to
him they did worse to people around the
world because maybe they ended up
killing him. We haven't talked about
that. But when I watched that movie, I
just kept thinking, you know, how do you
have a guy under surveillance 24/7
and yet you can't prevent his
assassination. I mean, that that
bothered me.
But even if we don't go They certainly
wanted him to commit suicide. They
wanted to destroy him as a figure. Now
you think about it. This is one of the
great recognized acknowledged heroes of
American life, right up there, probably
the top five of American heroes.
And and here was the FBI which is now
celebrated
by MSNBC, by the the liberal
establishment as the great people to
save us, right? We want them to have
more power, you know,
I mean, we even have
columns in in the New York Times and
everywhere urging more control of media
and surveillance and what have you.
So, what's going on? You you've been
there.
What what do what do you think about
this
surveillance society now?
Well, I first of all, I think that the
FBI is an outlaw organization.
Not only have I had my my home raided by
the FBI,
but I've had my home raided by the FBI
twice.
Twice.
I can't tell you what it feels like to
have 22 people break down your door,
all wearing windbreakers that say FBI on
the back of it as your neighbors come
out to record everything on their cell
phones, have them remain in your home
for 8 hours, in one case smashing a hole
in my in my kitchen wall over here with
a sledgehammer, and it's still there's
still a hole in the wall.
Dumping my potted plants out on the
floor
your camera so we could see the hole?
Yeah, I'll take it over there.
Dumping my potted plants out on the
floor, looking
allegedly looking for weapons, taking
literally all of my electronics,
and um
and then never charging me with a crime.
Let's see.
Right Oh, right
back in there. Can you see that?
it. Yeah, in the right corner. They said
that they had information that I was
storing weapons back there. I said, I
don't own any weapons.
But this is because you, who had been
a leading agent in capturing Yeah.
terrorists alleged terrorists and
warrants her in Afghanistan and risked
your life
and you were supposed to have
given the name of an open agent Yeah. to
a New York Times reporter. That was your
great crime. Your really great crime is
you revealed the torture program.
Yes. You're You're exactly right, Bob.
And I'll tell you another thing. So for
that reason
How many were there they broke into your
house? Twice? 20 24?
22. There were 22 of them. Yes. I don't
want to exaggerate. 22, not 24.
And they broke in and went through
everything of somebody you had been
honored by the CIA for your work, right?
You were I I got 12 exceptional
performance awards, the sustained
superior performance award, the
counterterrorism service medal, and the
merit meritorious service medal.
Yes. And so these agents though when
they came there was like trying to get
something on Martin Luther King or
they don't care that he won the Nobel
Prize. No. No. They don't care that John
Kiriakou because they're ordered to go
there
and find something. And then which is
after all what the
Fourth Amendment of the US Constitution
is supposed to protect you against
you know And And in fact In fact, the
FBI agent that physically put the
handcuffs on me was none other than
Peter Strzok
who has been you know implicated up to
his chin
in in this this partisan rebranding of
of the FBI.
Well, you should tell us about that.
He's the one who had the
what girlfriend or wife that also had a
high ranking
Correct. Yeah, he was cheating on his
wife with with an attorney at the FBI
and he was the one that was exchanging
these text messages with his girlfriend
uh about Donald Trump and they're not
going to stand for Donald Trump's
election and they're going to take him
down and they're going to block
everything he tries to do and he just
made it so partisan, so stupidly. So,
he's part of an agency that went after
Martin Luther King and was going to
smear him for being unfaithful to his
wife. But, here's this top FBI agent,
two of them, and they're doing what they
alleged that Martin Luther King did,
right? That's right.
self-righteous about it. And and just as
an aside, Bob, something that that I
have found to be very important over the
last couple of days, Jim Bamford, who is
a gifted writer and researcher, who
wrote really the definitive book on NSA
years ago, is out with a
underestimates it. He is the first
person in this country Yes.
to make us aware That's right.
of the surveillance state. I mean, it's
incredible.
Yeah. Yeah.
Well, he's out with a new book today.
Oh. Um about What's the title? Do you
have Do you have Do you have the title?
Yeah, I'll find it.
it. We could be the first to push it.
Well, well,
well, no, he does great work. Oh, he
does great work. Uh let's see.
It is called
Let me find it.
Spy Fail. Well, we're doing reality TV
and radio here. Yeah.
Yes. It's called Spy Fail, one word,
Foreign Spies, Moles, Saboteurs, and the
Collapse of America's
Counterintelligence. Now, what what he's
saying in this book
is that
over the last 10 years, the FBI has lost
10 of its China intelligence sources. 10
people have been either killed by the
Chinese government or arrested for
working on behalf of the FBI. Why is
that?
Because
Peter Strzok's counterintelligence unit
at the FBI had a Chinese mole in it.
And the mole was a former CIA operations
officer
who was directed to go to the CIA and
then later on to the FBI as a Chinese
translator.
This guy was arrested quietly in 2019
and is awaiting trial in Hawaii of all
places. Why isn't this front-page news?
There was a Chinese mole inside the FBI
and we're now just learning about it
thanks to Jim Bamford?
That tells me that there's something
grossly wrong with the mainstream media
here.
But let's get back to the story of of of
of what you learned from this movie
because I I I was shocked. I mean, you
know, I
got my own files and everything. So, I
was not naive about the FBI.
But the idea
and this is again I want to remind
people before the modern surveillance
technology where you know, they know
everything. I mean, how far you read in
a book and you know, and what you
emailed and and the people should
remember the Fourth Amendment was
considered the most important addition
to the Constitution by most of the
founders because they said this was how
the King of England was able to destroy
any independent thought in the colonies
because they could do warrantless
churches and come storming into your
house to
searches and come into your house and
find plant and find evidence and so
forth. And so, Adams and all of these
people, John Adams, said this is the
most important. The American Revolution
was born with
you know assertion and
of the right to to protect your
domicile, your house. As you can see
that goes back to the Magna Carta. You
now have a culture which takes what what
Hoover did
up to the I mean my God it's like you
know can we go across the street or can
we go to the moon? They can do anything
now. They can manipulate, they can make
an alternative reality. They can fake
sex scenes and movies and everything.
Yes they can. They're called deep fakes.
Yeah and and they can do all that and
that's being cheered on though. Oh yeah.
Amazing thing you know and including by
the so called liberals.
So I that's why I wanted to talk to you.
I I I
the irony that we now celebrate as we
should Martin Luther King the man who
you know everybody forgets we were in a
deeply segregated society at the time in
the mid 50s when when Martin Luther King
was leading a
the bus you know used to be able to
desegregate buses in Montgomery and all
that and and the movie reminds us of
that. We can't the US Army
was segregated, the Navy was only
desegregated in 47. We supposedly fought
a war for democracy and freedom with a
segregated military, racially segregated
military. Baseball the national pastime
was segregated
until Jackie Robinson.
You know so Martin Luther King's efforts
to desegregate were pioneering.
And the courage involved and the idea
that at the time when he was showing the
greatest courage and also as a minister
telling us about the larger moral issues
and the importance of non-violence
worldwide that our secret police agency
was
with that with
out to get this guy to kill himself. And
some would remember to argue maybe they
sat silently by while he was killed.
Oh, I think I think they did actually.
You know, at the very end of this film
uh
you you can't see their faces but you
hear their voices. These are These are
the voices of two of the FBI agents who
were involved in the surveillance of
Martin Luther King at the Lorraine Motel
in Memphis where he was assassinated. Uh
and they interviewed Jim Comey which
made no sense to me. But anyway, um
these FBI agents are saying that they
were doing the surveillance that night
and
saw the whole thing unfold.
Now,
we have something
should mention to people that the Martin
Luther King was at the his most
controversial moment because he was
challenging when he challenged the war
in Vietnam his point was you're spending
all of these resources, you know,
destroying these other people. You're
not going to have any money for your war
on poverty. And without economic
justice, without dealing with the root
causes of poverty, of which segregation
had quite a bit to do with the racial
basis of poverty, you're going to fail
to to bring about a a freer society. So
he was making his point. Lyndon Johnson
was upset about his, you know, opposing
the war and suddenly he didn't have the
protection of Johnson who who had uh uh
signed the, you know, change in law uh
and
uh and was an ally of of King. King was
an ally of Johnson at one point. Now, by
taking on the war, he broke his ties to
the Johnson administration. They
unleashed J. Edgar Hoover. And so here
he is down there at this rally,
organizing, supporting garbage workers
in their strike. He's going to lead this
poor people's campaign to Washington,
embarrassing the Johnson administration.
The FBI had him under closer
surveillance that night than they
probably ever did. Yes.
the target and they were unleashed by
Johnson uh to do their their their their
deeds and and he man and he's
assassinated.
And you know, that that
leads to a lot of other questions.
Um they interview Andrew Young uh in in
this film. Andrew Young, of course, was
a was a lieutenant of Martin Luther
King. He was the mayor He went on to
become the mayor of Atlanta. He went on
to become the US ambassador to the
United Nations. Andrew Young's a giant
in his own right.
And he and others around King at the
time
said that they never believed that James
Earl Ray
uh killed Martin Luther King.
They believed that it was the FBI or
somebody working for the FBI.
Uh James Earl Ray was later arrested at
Heathrow Airport in London with a false
Canadian passport. Actually with two
false Canadian passports
um trying to get to Brussels. Uh he was
on the run.
He at first confessed to killing King,
but then later said that he was a dupe
and that he didn't have anything to do
with it. There are a lot of people,
including African-American leaders,
national leaders, and family members of
Martin Luther King who believe that
James Earl Ray was innocent and that the
killer was either the FBI or somebody
working on behalf of the FBI.
We're going to end this, but
I want to get across the point of your
column, which people should read.
Original Source Consortium News, which
is now wildly attacked and publication
Yes. started by this fellow Perry, who
was a very good journalist, run by
journalists, but now, you know, they're
you know,
the New York Times even celebrates
mainstream
media, celebrates destroying any
alternative website, certainly
Consortium News. But,
the whole thing is we people don't
realize what the Church Commission
revealed. Mhm. They revealed basically,
you know, the COINTELPRO, the dirty
tricks, the setting people up, the
destroying
people. And that's what was happening to
Martin Luther King. Yes. They tried to
label him first as some kind of
communist agent. That didn't go over,
then as some kind of pervert or
something, but destroy him. The end
justifies the means. That is what the
deep state why it's deep. Yes. Because
what they're doing
if it's in the light of day, would be
considered reprehensible. That's what we
mean by the deep state, right?
That's right. That's exactly what we
mean mean by the deep state. Let me Let
me just finish
on on this note. Um the day after my
arrest in 2012,
um
there there there were two things that
happened. One, there was an article in
the the Washington Times, which is the
conservative paper, it's owned by the
Unification Church, the Moonies. Um
an FBI agent, an anonymous one of
course, um said that I was a bad actor.
Those were the words that he used. I was
a bad actor, and that I was working on
behalf of the terrorists.
Okay, ridiculous. I had blown the
whistle on an illegal, immoral, and
unethical program.
Um
the other thing was that
I was charged with confirming the name
of his former CIA colleague. That name
was never made public. But, at the same
time, there was a former CIA officer in
Bethesda, Maryland, who had been thrown
out of the CIA. He was a disgruntled
former officer. He had a website in
which he named seven former CIA officers
and was never arrested.
And then the director of the CIA, David
Petraeus, confirmed the name of 10
covert CIA officers to his adulterous
girlfriend. He was never prosecuted for
that. And I said to my lawyers at the
time, well, why aren't they charged with
this crime?
And the the quick answer was because
they didn't blow the whistle on the
torture program.
The point being
out one of the startling examples of
Panetta when he was Yeah. That's even
back revealing the name
I wrote a piece in the LA Times about
that. Leon Panetta did exactly the same
thing
to a roomful of un
cleared people, including journalists.
yeah, well, also there were people from
Hollywood who were going to make the
Mark Bowden and Kathryn Bigelow.
Yeah, they were going to make a movie
that ended up praising the CIA and
actually suggesting that torture,
erroneously, lying really, is suggesting
that torture was
critical to the capture of Bin Laden.
That's right.
if you
defend if you defend torture, then you
will be given the names of
the sealed,
you know, team that
got Bin Laden, which would be a very
important secret cuz their lives could
be threatened and so forth. And
but they didn't go to jail and Leon
Panetta didn't. So, that's a point and
the the hypocrisy. But, you know, do I
got a last word?
No, I'm so glad that you I'm so glad
that you reached out to me over this. I
think this is a very important topic and
even though what happened to Martin
Luther King happened some 55 years ago,
it's still just as current today. Such
It's just as important today um as it
was in 1968.
Oh, it because of the modern technology,
it's more important. You can alter
reality. You can learn and and you know,
even in in that situation, we don't
really know what was going on because we
got FBI agents and they're putting
things in the margin That's right.
suggesting, you know, worse things
happen and so forth and they're writing
it and distorting it. Uh but now, my
goodness, you know, what what you can
And we've had We've had leading
politicians already have to leave
office, you know, the former governor of
New York versus allegedly was involved
with some prostitute or something. Boom,
they're gone. No longer a possible
presidential candidate and so forth. And
so it it's it's odd that Yeah, it's
great that Martin Luther King survived.
And however, I would warn people
uh in 2027, those documents are supposed
to be released. That's right.
And I suspect there will be people who
use that to finally destroy
uh the image of arg- and no
unquestionably the
five greatest Americans of all time in
terms of their positive impact on the
society. They'll be still people
chomping at the bit to do him in.
You know.
That's right. That is right. It'll never
end. Yeah.
Sadly, but again, we're here to warn
people and uh okay, so I you were the
real CIA, I'm the poor man's sure
intelligence. That's where I got the
word and so forth actually given to me
by the station. Want to thank you, John
Kiriakou, a great American punished uh
for what? Almost 2 years in prison for
uh really uh coming out
uh
and exposing the torture program. That
was it and they went after you and what
did you say 22 of these FBI agents? They
couldn't go in there and bust up Martin
Luther King's place cuz that would have
been too much news
and what they could do it to you.
All right, on that note, I want to thank
by the way before we get off here. I
want to thank Laura
Condijerian and Christopher Horwood
station KCRW in Santa Monica great
station NPR station for hosting these
podcasts. Joshua Sheer our executive
producer the JKW Foundation in the
memory of a very independent and
important journalist Jean Stein for
helping fund these shows. See you next
week with another edition of Shear
Intelligence. Take care.